英文字幕&时间轴：Red Bee Media Ltd
翻译&校对：  the Doctor
1726年3月28日
On 28th March, 1726,
一口棺材被抬到了威斯敏斯特大教堂
a coffin was carried into Westminster Abbey.
棺材里的人曾经位高权重
In it was the body of a man who had held high office,
虽然他不是政客
although he wasn't a politician.
他曾将别人送上绞刑架 虽然他不是司法部官员
He had had men hanged, although he wasn't a member of the judiciary.
他写了很多关于《圣经》的文章
And he'd written extensively on Scriptures,
虽然他也不是牧师
although he was no cleric or priest.
他的棺材是由大法官
His coffin was carried by the Lord Chancellor,
两位公爵和三位伯爵抬到这的
two dukes and three earls.
这个人就是伊萨克・牛顿
That man was Isaac Newton.
能够下葬威斯敏斯特大教堂
To be buried in Westminster Abbey
通常是国王和贵族才有的荣誉
was an honour usually reserved for kings and nobles,
牛顿这样的平民是没有这样特权的
not commoners like Newton.
但牛顿并不是个平凡的人
But Newton was no ordinary man.
这里写道
Even here, it's written,
“众人因这样杰出的存在而欣喜”
"Mortals rejoice that there has existed such an ornament of the human race".
牛顿是第一位自然哲学家
Now, Newton was the first natural philosopher,
用现在的话来说 就是科学家
or scientist, as we now call him,
而人们以这种方式纪念他
to be honoured in this way.
但他一定不是最后一个
But he certainly wasn't the last.
这是詹姆斯・克拉克・麦克斯韦
And here is James Clerk Maxwell.
这是迈克尔・法拉第
Here, Michael Faraday.
这是保罗・狄拉克
And here, Paul Dirac.
人们还将他描述电子运动的方程
With his equation describing the behaviour of the electron
刻在了威斯敏斯特大教堂的地面上
inscribed into the stone on the floor of Westminster Abbey.
英国以这种方式
It's perhaps no coincidence
纪念其杰出的科学家
that a country that honours its leading scientists in this way
因此拥有数量众多的领路人和改革者
has produced far more than its fair share
也就不奇怪了
of trailblazers and innovators.
解码DNA 解释遗传的科学家们
Men and women who explained heredity by decoding DNA.
为每项太空计划提供物理学基础的科学家们
Who provided the physics for every space programme ever conceived.
利用万维网转变人类交流方式的科学家们
And transformed communication for ever with the World Wide Web.
这个系列里 我想考察
In this series, I want to explore Britain's pivotal role
英国在创建现代科学中发挥的关键作用
in creating modern science.
发掘每一个为现代科学做出贡献的人物
Reveal the characters who have made science what it is today.
揭示英国在过去的300年中
Show how Britain has used its scientific strength
如何运用其科学优势
for over 300 years.
探究英国科学路在何方
And explore what the future holds for British science.
英国科学家不断地
British scientists have made and continue to make,
做出重大科学发现
some of the great scientific discoveries.
但从历史的角度看
But of equal importance from a historical perspective,
同等重要的是科学研究手段的发展
was the development of the means by which we do science.
提出理论 实验论证
The idea that you build theories, you test them by experiment
最后发表结果
and you publish the results.
这就是科学方法
This is known as the scientific method.
也是科学的基础
It is the bedrock of science.
这是由英国科学家率先使用并不断完善的
And it was developed and first used, to a large extent, here in Britain.
这里是英国皇家学会
This is The Royal Society.
世界顶尖科学家的联盟
A fellowship of the world's most eminent scientists
成立于1660年
that has existed since 1660.
其成员几乎包括所有科学史上的重要人物
Its members include virtually all of the great names in science.
从达尔文到法拉第
From Charles Darwin to Michael Faraday.
就是这些人的构想和研究
These are people whose ideas and investigations
改变了我们对自然界的理解
have transformed our understanding of the natural world.
他们改变世界的行为
That they were able to perform such a transformation
已足够引人注目
is remarkable enough.
同样值得注意的是
But what's also remarkable
很多皇家学会成员
is that many of The Royal Society's members
都将他们的杰出成就
would've traced their towering achievements
归功到一个人的研究上
back to the work of one man.
艾萨克・牛顿爵士
Sir Isaac Newton.
这是牛顿的死亡面具
This is Newton's death mask.
他死后
It's a plaster cast of his face
依照他面部做成的石膏模型
that would've been taken moments after he died.
趁尸体还有未凉
And the technique was to make these masks
人们做成这些面具
whilst the body was still warm.
这东西看起来确实很可怕
And it's really quite an eerie thing to look at.
如果你将牛顿看待成一位物理学家
When you think of Newton as a physicist,
那么就会认为牛顿就是一堆抽象理论的集合
you think of Newton as almost an abstract set of theories.
你知道 F = MA 力等于质量乘以加速度
You know, F = MA, force equals mass times acceleration.
想起他的万有引力定律
You think of his universal law of gravitation.
第一个普适的物理定律
That first universal, physical law that's still used to this day
今天依然应用此项定律向太阳系边缘或之外发射宇宙飞船
to send spacecraft to the edge of the solar system and beyond.
但看看这个
But when you look at this,
你会发现一个不同的牛顿
you see a different Newton.
仅仅是一个人
You see Newton, the man.
牛顿并不是很容易相处
Newton certainly wasn't the easiest person to get along with.
他强势 不怀好意
He was obsessive, malicious
而且易怒
and prone to outbursts of rage.
但他的工作方式
But there was something quite extraordinary
也有些不同寻常
about the way that he worked.
在人类依然信仰魔法的年代
In an age when people still believed in magic,
牛顿提出了革命性的理论框架
Newton devised a revolutionary theoretical framework
人们可以以此准确地探索自然的本质
with which to accurately investigate the nature of the world.
1642年 牛顿出生在
Newton was born in 1642
处于过渡期的英格兰
into an England that was a country in transition.
那年 英国内战正式爆发
That was the start of the English Civil War.
那是个人们仍在到处搜寻女巫的国家
It was a country where they were still hunting for witches.
但也是个科学 理性思考
But also, it was a country where science,
开始蓬勃发展的国家
where rational thought, where reason were beginning to flower.
当时 一个伟大的问题
Now, at the time, one of the great questions
是关于光的本质
was about the nature of light.
当时人们已经知道 如果你用太阳光照射棱镜
It was known that if you take a prism and shine sunlight through it,
棱镜则会将太阳光
then it splits that sunlight
分散成彩虹的颜色
into all the colours of the rainbow.
而问题就是为什么
The question was why.
之前主流的科学观点
Now, the prevailing scientific view
太阳光是完美的
was that sunlight must be perfect.
这要一路追溯到亚里士多德和其他古希腊哲学家
This dated all the way back to Aristotle and the Ancient Greeks.
来自上天的东西
How could something that comes from the heavens
怎么可能不是完美的
be anything other than perfect?
当时大部分人对此的解释
The common explanation for the appearance of the colours
是棱镜带来了杂质
was that they were impurities added by the prism
污染了纯净的白光
to the pure white light.
牛顿则认为这些颜色
Newton thought that the colours
原来就存在于白光中
were already present in the white sunlight.
但牛顿的可贵之处在于
But what set Newton apart
他设计了实验
was the fact that he devised and performed an experiment
并以此验证自己的假设
to test his hypothesis.
这就是牛顿的天才设计
Then, and here's the genius,
他在彩虹中放置了一条细缝
he introduced a slit into that rainbow beam.
这样他就可以分离出单色光
And that allowed him to isolate a particular colour of light
然后再将单色光照向第二个棱镜
and shine that into a second prism.
接着他观察有色光在墙壁上的偏转
Then he looked for the deflection of the coloured light onto his wall.
看 就在那
You can see that over there.
我现在将红光换成绿光
Now, look what happens
看看接下来会发生什么
when I move the red light across the slit, to the green light.
你会发现 照射在棱镜上的绿光
On the wall, what you see is green light into the prism
也就是发出的绿光
equals green light out.
这意味着颜色本身是纯净的
Now, that implies that the colours themselves are pure.
棱镜并没有添加或除去任何东西
The prism is not adding or subtracting anything.
这表明实验验证了牛顿的假设是正确的
That means that Newton's hypothesis was shown to be correct.
有色光本身
The colours themselves
就是光线的基本组成部分
are the basic building blocks of light.
白光是由所有的有色光组合起来的
And white light is made up of all those individual colours.
这太神奇了
That's genius.
牛顿率先使用今天所谓的“科学方法”
Newton was one of the first to interrogate nature
探索自然
using the principles of what we now call the scientific method.
换句话说 他观察世界
In other words, he observed the world,
提出理论解释观察到的现象
came up with theories to explain what he saw,
接着用实验验证这些理论十分正确
then tested them with experiments to see if he was right.
这种方法的优势在于
The power of this approach
它意图排除已先入为主的构想
is that it aims to remove preconceived ideas.
这么做 我们就可以
And in doing so, deliver a more accurate description
更加准确地描述自然界
of the natural world.
但他虽然思考清晰 实验技巧娴熟
But for all his clarity of thought and experimental technique,
但似乎没有意识到
Newton himself seems to have been strangely unaware
自己工作的重要性
of the importance of his work.
这本书十分珍贵
This is a priceless book.
它是牛顿著作《自然哲学的数学原理》
It is the first handwritten manuscript
的第一份手稿
of Newton's great masterpiece, the Principia.
书里第一次
It's in here the first time
描述了万有引力定律
that the universal law of gravitation is outlined.
他提出的运动定律
It's also his laws of motion
也解释了宇宙万物的运动
that say how objects move around in the universe.
这几乎是你大一整年
It's pretty much everything you do
要学的物理
in the first year of an undergraduate degree in physics.
而这本书背后的故事也令人着迷
And the story behind the writing of this book is fascinating.
它也揭露了牛顿的其他方面
It reveals a lot about Newton.
天文学家埃德蒙多・哈雷曾说过
The astronomer Edmond Halley said,
是否存在一个外有引力定律
"Is it true that there's a universal law of gravity
可以解释所有星球的可观测到的运行轨道
"that can explain the observed orbits of the planets?"
牛顿说 我已经证明了 几年前就证明过了
Newton said, "Yeah, I've proved it. I proved it a couple of years ago."
然后他开始找笔记
And he went to look for his notes,
但他找不到
and the story is that he couldn't find them.
接着他坐下来 开始重写这个证明过程
And so he just sat down and wrote the whole thing out again.
和哈雷的对话引出了整部《自然哲学的数学原理》
And it's that conversation with Halley that led to the Principia.
我们会惊奇地发现
So, it's interesting to speculate
如果把这事交给牛顿处理
that if it had been left up to Newton,
科学史上最伟大的著作
then maybe the greatest work in the history of science
根本就不会发表了
wouldn't have been published at all.
探索自然的乐趣对牛顿来说也已经足够了
The joy of exploring nature was enough for Newton.
著述 与别人分享知识
And the act of writing it down and sharing his knowledge
可能就是次要的了
with others was somehow secondary.
牛顿本身也充满了矛盾
Newton was certainly a man of contradictions.
他生活在17世界中叶
Given that he lived and worked in the middle of the 17th century.
站在理性时代的开端
He stood at the cusp, at the dawn of the Age of Reason.
毫无疑问 他处在两个世界中
And so, he was undoubtedly a man with feet in both worlds.
神秘世界和科学世界
The mystical and the scientific.
他是占星家 炼金术士
He was an astrologer, an alchemist,
但他也明白
but he was also a man who understood
什么是科学家
what it is to be a scientist almost innately.
他说我们可以
He said that the nature of things
通过物体间的相互作用
can be most naturally and securely deduced
而不是通过自己的直觉
by their operations one upon another,
推断出事物的本质
rather than upon the senses.
他想表达的是了解自然运转的唯一方法就是
By which he meant that the only way to understand how nature works
观察它
is to look at it
然后运用理性思考
and then use logic and reason
理解并解释自己观察到的现象
to understand and explain what you see.
从表面上看来
On the face of it, it seems baffling
科学方法经过了很长时间才出现
that the scientific method took so long to emerge.
毕竟 牛顿就生活在几个世纪前
After all, Newton lived just a few hundred years ago.
问题的一部分就是
Part of the problem is that our world
我们生活的世界是个复杂且令人困惑的地方
is a complicated and baffling place.
但如果你将世界简化 那么就容易理解多了
But it's much easier to understand if you simplify it.
通过观察彩虹就可能推测出光的本质
It is possible to deduce the nature of light by investigating a rainbow.
但牛顿设计了一个可控可重复的实验
But by creating a controllable, repeatable experiment,
验证了自己的假设
Newton was able to support his hypothesis
接着将理解
and then transfer that understanding
扩展到实验室外更复杂的世界里
to the much more complex world outside the laboratory.
这个合理系统的方法
It's this logical, systematic approach
使英国科学
that has enabled British science
解释了自然界中
to shed light on nature's great mysteries,
小到物质结构 大到行星的轨道的难题
from the structure of matter to the orbits of the planets.
也因其在医学和科技上的应用
It's also improved our lives through its application
提高了我们的生活水平
to medicine and technology.
牛顿奠定基础的250年后
And 250 years after Isaac Newton laid its foundation,
科学方法
the scientific method
是整个英国在其黑暗时期的灯塔
provided Britain a lifeline in our darkest hour.
新闻影片：纳粹的计划就是断绝英国的粮食和军需品
NEWSREEL: 'Nazi strategy is to starve Britain of food and munitions.
派出大量纳粹潜水艇
'Scores of Nazi U-boats set out to harry the ships
掠夺向英国运输必要物资的船只
'that bring essential stocks and supplies to Britain.'
1940年 美国派出护航舰向英国运输粮食和军需品
In 1940, the convoys bringing supplies of food and ammunition
但它们都因德国潜水艇
from America to Britain were suffering a frightening rate of attrition
遭受到严重损失
at the hands of German U-boats.
丘吉尔和其他人
And Churchill and others genuinely thought
想到我们数周内就可能输掉这场战争
that we were within weeks of losing the war.
但最后还是成功摆脱了困境
Now, salvation came, not in the form of a new weapon system,
并不是因为造出了新的武器系统或者飞机或军舰
a new aircraft or warship,
而是因为一群有献身精神的人们
but at the hands of a few dedicated people,
可以说是天才
geniuses even,
拿起纸币
with pencils and paper,
在白金汉郡小屋内做出的努力
working here in sheds in Buckinghamshire.
布莱切利园是英国二战期间
Bletchley Park was the centre
破解德国密码的基地
for British code-breaking during World War II.
就是在这 分析拦截到的德国信息
It was here that intercepted German messages were brought for analysis.
杰瑞・罗伯茨上尉
Captain Jerry Roberts was part of the group
就参加了破解德国信息的计划
assigned the task of decrypting the daily flow of communications.
他当时刚毕业 有法语和德语的学位
He'd just graduated with a degree in French and German,
但他对国际象棋和填字游戏的浓重兴趣
but it was his keen interest in chess and crosswords
使他拥有了这项工作
that landed him the job.
你乐于接受
Did you take delight in just the intellectual challenge
每日破解敌方密码的挑战吗
of breaking the code every day?
因为你必须得保持高度的专注度
Did that almost, I don't know, remove from your mind
这有没有使你忽略了其他重要的事情
the bigger picture because you had to focus so much on that act?
我们都十分高兴破解工作取得了巨大的进展
We greatly enjoyed the process of breaking, you know?
确实很有趣
It was great fun.
老实说
I have to be quite honest
我们并没太在意会对战争产生什么影响
and say, we were not thinking too much about the impact on the war,
我们只是在考虑如何取得更大的进展
we were thinking about how we could get a bit further along, you know?
是的
Yeah.
纳粹无线电通信设备
The Nazi war machine ran on radio communications,
加密了战场上个部队
coded signals between the forces in the field
和柏林指挥地之间的信号
and the high command in Berlin.
大部分信息都被恩尼格玛密码机加密了
Most of the general traffic was encoded by a machine called Enigma.
罗伯茨抵达布莱切利之前
By the time Gerry Roberts arrived at Bletchley,
同盟国就因阿兰・图灵的工作
the Allies had broken the Enigma code thanks to the
破解了谜语机密码
mathematical work done by Alan Turing
还有另一个原因就是获取了正在工作的谜语机
and also because a working Enigma machine had been captured.
但更大的收获则是
But the big prize was another code that was
获取了为柏林最高级通讯保留下来的另一套密码
reserved for the highest level signals from Berlin.
它采取某些和谜语机一样的原则
It used some of the same principles as Enigma,
但却更加复杂
but it was far more complicated.
纳粹高级将领称之为洛仑兹密码
The Nazi high command knew this code as the Lorenz cipher.
而同盟国则称之为金枪鱼
The Allies called it Tunny.
金枪鱼拥有不止一级两级加密
Tunny had not one, not two,
它有三级加密
but three levels of encryption.
也从未被破译过
It should never, ever have been broken.
要不是因为害羞谦虚的比尔・塔特
And it might not have been were it not for the scientific approach
采取化难为易的科学方法
taken by a shy and unassuming man called Bill Tutte
这套密码也不会被破译
of reducing the complex to the simple.
接近三个月里
He dedicated every waking hour
他醒着的每一分钟都在破译密码
for nearly three months to cracking the code.
我和他坐在同一间办公室
I was actually sitting in the same office as he was
他在那工作
when he was doing it,
而我望着他
and I saw him staring into the middle distance,
看他摆弄自己的笔
twiddling his pencil,
在纸上演算着
and making counts on reams of paper,
我一直想知道他到底成功了没有
and I used to wonder whether he was getting anything done!
天啊 他终于成功了
My goodness, he was.
这就是人类伟大的壮举
It was an extraordinary feat of the mind.
太不可思议了 你知道塔特是如何做到的吗
I find it remarkable. Do you understand how Tutte did it?
部分是些计算 但主要是逻辑思考
It's partly mathematics, but mostly logic.
如果这个是这个 那个是那个
If this is this and that is that,
那么它必须遵循这个很可能是其他
then it follows that this must be the other conclusion.
同盟国里没有人见过产生金枪鱼的设备
No-one on the Allied side had seen the machine that produced Tunny.
所以塔特利用他的头脑和一支笔就破译了这套密码
So the fact that Tutte cracked the code with little more than his brain
这是天才才能完成的超凡工作
and a pencil is a testament to an extraordinary work of genius.
同盟国记录了已经发送过两次的
The Allies had recorded a message that had been sent twice
利用金枪鱼加密过的信息
using the same Tunny encryption or key.
就是这一个小小失误使
It was this tiny lapse in procedure that gave Tutte a way in
塔特有机会破解了整个系统
to crack the entire system.
他的方法十分科学
His approach was scientific.
因为所有信息是相似的 但不完全相同
Because the messages were similar, but not identical,
而且使用统一的密匙
and they used the same key,
所有他推测出一定存在重复的结构
he knew there would be repeated patterns
他如果可以通过仔细观察发现这些结构
and if he could find those patterns by careful observation,
那么就可以破解整套密码
he could crack the code.
他最后找到了一种结构
He eventually did find a pattern
这个结构里隐藏着一个素数 41
and in that pattern, was hidden a prime number - 41.
因此他提出假设
His hypothesis was this was the number of settings possible
41可能是金枪鱼密码机第一圈转子上的档数
for the first of Tunny's scrambling wheels
事实验证了他的假设
and this turned out to be correct.
这也是破解整个密码机的关键
It was the key to unlocking the entire cipher.
身为译解密码者
As a cryptographer,
我很难相信他竟然做到了
I find that almost impossible to believe that he did it.
有人称之为上个世纪伟大的智力创举
One man called it the outstanding mental feat of the last century.
不是战争 上个世纪
Not the war, the last century.
和恩尼格玛密码机破译者不一样 塔特从没见过
Unlike the Enigma code-breakers, Tutte had never seen the machine
纳粹如何使用设备产生代码
the Nazis used to produce the code that he cracked.
但仅通过逻辑思考 仔细观察
But by using logic, careful observation
以及大胆假设
and by producing testable hypotheses,
他就成功破解了密码机的工作原理
he managed to determine exactly how it worked.
这意味着我们有可能造出
And that meant it was possible to build a machine
一台机器自动破译加密信号
to automatically decipher the coded signals as they were issued.
比尔・塔特利用科学方法就是同盟国
By applying a scientific approach, Bill Tutte allowed the Allies
可以监听纳粹高官说过的每一个字
to listen in to virtually every word uttered by the Nazi high command,
而产生的结果也是惊人的
and the consequences were breathtaking.
我也相当怀疑有时我们的将军会比德国将军
I strongly suspect that our generals sometimes saw the text
先看到解密后的信息
of the messages before the blessed German generals did!
艾森豪威尔将军在战后曾说
General Eisenhower said, after the war,
布莱奇利的破译工作
that Bletchley decrypts helped shorten the war
将战争缩短了至少两年
by at least two years.
至少两年
At LEAST two years.
而这场战争里
And this was a war
每年平均会有一千万人丧生
in which ten million people died each year on average.
比尔・塔特完成了似乎不可能的任务
Bill Tutte had achieved the seemingly impossible.
他仅通过逻辑原理
He'd done it by applying the principles of logic
就做到了
enshrined in the scientific method.
但这仅仅是故事的一部分
But that's only part of the story.
在他还没听过金枪鱼或布莱切利园的很久以前
Tutte was fascinated by problem-solving
他就着迷于解决问题
long before he'd ever heard of Tunny or Bletchley Park.
和牛顿 达尔文 法拉第
Like Newton, Darwin, Faraday
和其他数不尽的科学们一样
and countless other scientists before and since,
塔特爱好 甚至着迷于
Tutte was interested in, perhaps even obsessed by,
了解事物如何运转
discovering how things work.
理查德・博切尔兹就是当代的塔特
Richard Borcherds is a latter-day Tutte.
首先我先将平方先加起来 0的平方 加上1的平方 加上2的平方
..First I start adding up squares, so I take nought squared, plus one squared, plus two squared...
他现在是加州大学伯克利分校的数学教授
He's a professor of mathematics at the University of California at Berkeley.
这是一个椭圆模函数
An elliptic modular function looks like this...
另一位尝试破解
Another British scientist on a quest
似乎不能破解的密码的英国科学家
to solve an apparently uncrackable code.
我不仅尝试理解宇宙如何运转
What I'm doing is trying to understand
也要搞清楚它为什么存在 为什么运转
not just how the universe works, but why it exists or why it works.
这个问题听起来很可怕
That's a very scary question that...
你知道 宇宙为什么存在
You know, why does the universe exist at all?
过去的15年里 理查德一直试图解决抽象问题
Richard has spent the last 15 years trying to solve an abstract problem
它是量子场理论的核心
that lies at the heart of quantum field theory,
而量子场理论最好地
our best current description
描述了自然界的基础
of the building blocks of the natural world.
这个问题已经困扰了数学家将近一个世纪
It's something that has defeated mathematicians for almost a century,
但理查德不为所动
but Richard is undeterred.
他每天都在攻克这个难题
He spends many hours a day working on the problem.
看我工作和看我睡觉
Watching me work is pretty much indistinguishable
没什么大的不同
from watching me sleeping.
我一般会这样的坐很久
I'd generally just be sort of sitting there like this...
就是想问题
for a long time, just thinking.
大部分时候你问我这个月有什么进展
Most months you ask me what I've produced this month
我一般会说 嗯 我发现这个想法行不通
and I will say, "Well, I've discovered this idea doesn't work."
就是这样
And that's it.
大部分的工作不是在计算
Most of the work is not in doing calculations,
而是搞清楚要计算什么
but in trying to figure out what calculations to do.
而这要花要用多年的时间
That's the part of mathematics that takes years
却毫无进展
and years without really getting anywhere.
毫无疑问 理查德智力超群
Richard has, without question, an unusual mind.
和布莱切利园一样聪明
A mind similar to the Bletchley Park code-breakers.
他连续多年完成看似不能完成的任务
One capable of dedicating years on end to the almost incomprehensible task
理解支撑着宇宙的抽象数学
of understanding the abstract mathematics that underpins the universe.
虽然他付出了超出常人的努力
But although his dedication may appear extreme,
但执念似乎是所有科学家拥有的共性
it seems that an element of obsessiveness is something that many scientists share.
从牛顿到迪拉克
From Isaac Newton to Paul Dirac,
从麦克斯韦到塔特再到博切尔兹
James Clerk Maxwell to Bill Tutte and Richard Borcherds,
英国不断地涌现出发愤图强的科学家
Britain has produced an array of driven scientists
为科学进步做出了重大贡献
who have contributed enormously to our understanding.
他们的脱颖而出并不是因为他们的财富 权力 或者恶名
They stand out, not because of their wealth, power or notoriety,
而来自他们独特的思考方式
but because of the way they thought.
原因可能是他们将科学放在了首要位置
Which might be the reason that they were drawn to science in the first place.
拜伦・科恩教授研究了科学家们的心理状态后
Professor Simon Baron-Cohen studies the psychology of scientists
发现大多数科学家有一些共同的特征
and has discovered that many of them share some specific characteristics.
研究对象中的大部分
Many people in the population
都喜欢在聊天时经常变换话题
are quite happy to flit from one topic to another.
他们乐意聊天 但都不想超过半个小时
They're happy to chat about something, but they don't want to go on about it for half an hour,
更别说几小时 几天 几周了
let alone many, many hours, or days or weeks.
我想 拥有科学头脑的人不想停留在一个话题上
And, I think, someone with a scientific mind often does want to stay on one topic,
无论在研究什么 他们都想更加深入地了解
they want to go deeper into whatever they're studying.
我笑是因为我也这样
Now, I'm grinning because I definitely see that in myself,
我太太也一定这么想的
and my wife would certainly say that that's the case.
一旦我聊起某些事
Once I start talking about something
我不太可能聊很久
I'm likely not to talk about anything else for a long time. Yeah.
这确实很有趣 我认识到了这一点
That's interesting, actually, cos I recognise that.
而且不会产生消极影响
Yeah, but it's not negative, that's the point.
我们在讨论重视深度而不是广度的头脑
That, effectively, we're talking about a mind that prioritises depth over breadth.
这以前常被看成是不好的行为
And that used to be seen as something negative,
你太执着自己痴迷的事物 人们不会鼓励你这么做的
that if you go too deeply into something you're obsessional and it should be discouraged.
但现在我们发现 除非你是飞机设计师
But what we can now see is that... Unless you're the aircraft designer that designed the aircraft
正设计自己要乘坐的飞机 这真是理想的工作啊
you're sitting on. In which case, it would be desirable!
我很庆幸飞机设计师十分执着
I'm delighted that the aircraft designer is obsessional, yeah. Yeah.
西蒙的研究又发现了
As part of his research, Simon has shown another trait
科学家身上更普遍的特征――对细节的注意
to be more common amongst scientists - attention to detail.
这个例子很好地显示了我们怎样观察你对细节的关注度
This is an example where we're looking at how well you can pick up detail.
你可以多快地在整个设计中找出目标性状
So, how quickly you can find the target shape hidden in the overall design.
科学家在这项试验中表现得比普通人优秀
Scientists are quicker at this test than non-scientists,
再一次强调 我们不是仅在讨论古怪的性格
and again, we're not just talking about eccentricity now,
其实我们在寻找某个特定的心理过程
we're actually looking at a specific psychological process.
西蒙通过调查问卷可以测量一个被他称为“系统化”的品质
Using a questionnaire, Simon has also measured a trait he calls "systemising".
这是驱动人们理解
This is the drive and ability that people have to understand
从天气到地图 从政治到引擎
how things work, from the weather to road maps,
大千事物运转的能力
from politics to car engines.
这些问题关于
There are questions in there about how interested
你对家里的电线有多大兴趣
you are in the electrical wiring in your house.
我十分感兴趣
I'm very interested in that.
嗯 那你就得分了 在这题上得了一份
So, you would probably score, you know, you'd score one point
还有很多类似的问题
on that item and there are lots of items of that kind.
小时候某次过生日 还收到过一个保险丝盒
I once got a fuse box for my birthday when I was young,
实际上是我要的 嗯 大概是12岁的时候 这是什么意思
I actually asked for a fuse box. Right. It was my 12th birthday or something, what does that say?
嗯 它在证实测试的有效性
Well, it's telling us that the test has validity.
耶 系统化头脑的标准
Yeah! It's a sign of a systematic mind.
另一项有趣的发现是
What's also interesting is that the personality trait
西蒙展示的科学家拥有的性格特质
Simon has shown to be characteristic of scientists
表现在自闭症儿童的身上
are expressed in their extreme in children with autism.
我们知道自闭症儿童往往有社交障碍
Kids with autism we know have difficulty socialising,
但他们通常十分留意细节
but they often have excellent attention to detail
他们喜欢在事物中寻找特定的模式 就像科学家一样
and they like to look for patterns in things, just like a little scientist really.
下面举个点灯开关的例子
An example might be electrical light switches,
他们想知道把开关扳到开或关
that they want to look at the effect of putting a light switch
会对整间房子产生什么效果
into different positions, the on and off position, all around the house.
嗯 这就是个实验 你说的很对 科学方法从根本上说
So it's experimentation. It is. Essentially the scientific method
就是孤立某个特定系统 然后
in action, just isolating a particular system and...
嗯 但这是在真实世界里
It is, but it's in the real world, absolutely.
我的意思是 没有把科学家
I mean, there's no claim in which you would label scientists
贴上自闭症的标签 很可笑
as autistic in some sense, it's ridiculous.
确实没有
Absolutely not, that is ridiculous.
数据告诉我们 在相关的测验中
What the evidence is telling us is that on specific measures of relevance,
科学家的得分
scientists are just scoring mid-way
正好在自闭症患者和其他人之间
between people with autism and the rest of the population.
大部分人都能猜到
It will come as no surprise to most people,
科学家身上有某些特别的性格特征
that there are certain character traits that we associate with scientists,
想解构世界的想法
the idea that you want to deconstruct the world,
对最微小细节的留意
that you pay attention to the smallest details.
我发现我还是小孩的时候 身上就有一些特征
Actually, I can identify some of those traits in myself as a child.
西蒙问过我关于收集东西的问题
Some of the questions that Simon asked me about of collecting things...
我 我喜欢观察公交车 然后在名单上打勾
I was... I liked to spot buses and tick them off in a list,
我也喜欢观察火车
I liked to do the same with trains.
我还喜欢收集电路 绕起来 看它怎么工作
I also liked to collect electrical apparatus and wire it up and understand how it works.
我猜 回想起来 这些都预示着
And, I suppose, in retrospect, that may have marked me out
我长大后可能成为一名科学家
as being statistically more likely to be a scientist when I grew up.
科学家对研究对象的关注
Scientists' dedication to their subject may sometimes appear
有时可能会显得十分古怪甚至诡异
to be quirky or even eccentric.
但这来自于很多科学家都有的特性
But it stems from a trait that I think many scientists share -
对世界万物的好奇心
an all-embracing curiosity.
这是唯一一张亨利・卡文迪许的画像
This is the only picture of Henry Cavendish,
因为他不喜欢坐在那让别人给自己画像 事实上 他从未这么做过
and the reason is that he was very uncomfortable about sitting for portraits. In fact, he never did it.
所以这张照片是一位艺术家晚餐时瞟了他一眼
So this was done mainly by an artist who glimpsed him over dinner
然后仅凭记忆画出来的
and then sketched it from memory.
他显示了卡文迪许身上所有的古怪特质
It shows all the essential eccentric features of the man.
他戴着一顶
He's wearing a hat which has been described as something
仿佛来自上世纪的帽子
from the previous century.
他生活在18世纪
Remember, this is a man who was living in the 1700s,
可戴了一顶17世纪的三角帽
so he's got a 17th-century three-cornered hat.
他也经常穿同一件外套 他十分喜欢这件外套
And he always wore the same coat and he liked it
因为经常穿它
so much that every year when it wore out,
衣服每年都会破
because he wore it every day,
而他都会再定制一健一模一样的外套
he had a new one, exactly the same, tailored.
卡文迪什生命中的主要目的就是
Cavendish's main aim in life was to weigh, measure and classify
尽可能测量 分类宇宙中的万物
as many objects in the universe as he possibly could,
幸运的是 和当时很多科学家一样
and fortunately, like many scientists at the time,
他家境富裕 可以由他
he was fabulously wealthy so he was able to indulge his curiosity
做各种各样神奇的实验
with hundreds of extraordinary experiments.
就像
Like this one,
1766年他第一次描述的这个实验
which he first reported in 1766.
需要几块金属
It involves taking a metal,
这里我们用锌
we'll take zinc,
然后倒入
and then I'm going to pour
浓盐酸
concentrated hydrochloric acid onto the zinc.
接着把产生的气体导入肥皂溶液
Now I'm going to bubble the gas that's produced  into this soap solution,
现在这些气泡将充满这种气体
so these bubbles are now going to be filled with this gas,
要十分迅速 十分小心 点燃气体
and very quickly and carefully I'm going to light the gas.
GAS POPS
卡文迪什称它为
Now, Cavendish called that, not inappropriately,
易燃的气体
I suppose, "inflammable air".
现在都知道这种气体就是氢气
It's the gas that we now know as hydrogen.
GAS POPS
但卡文迪什并没有就此打住
But Cavendish didn't stop there,
他继续顽固地试图定量地研究氢气
he doggedly continued his quest to quantify hydrogen
希望能够描述氢气的各种特征
until he could describe every aspect of its existence.
他想知道他新发现的气体
So, he wanted to see how his newly discovered gas,
现在被称作氢气
hydrogen, as we now call it,
如何跟其他物质反应 也包括空气在内
reacted with other things, including air.
现在我要重现卡文迪什的实验
So, I'm going to repeat Cavendish's experiment again
但这次要使用烧瓶
but this time with a vessel.
我想将它充满氢气
What I'm going to do is fill it with hydrogen...
GAS HISSES
现在这里充满了易燃的气体 然后点燃它
So, that's full of inflammable air, and I'm going to light the spark.
COMPUTER BEEPS
LOUD BANG
刚才我们看到的是一个化学反应
Now, what you saw there was a chemical reaction,
氢气和空气反应 你要是近距离
the reaction of hydrogen with air, and if you look closely
观察烧瓶的里面
on the sides of the flask,
你会发现它是 它是湿的
you'll see that it's... Well, it's wet.
这是水 是整个化学反应的产物
That is water and it's appeared as a result of the chemical reaction.
卡文迪什身上充分表现了科学是什么
In many respects, Cavendish embodies what science
以及科学家是什么
and what being a scientist is all about.
他对世界的好奇心驱动着他
His curiosity about the world drove him to design experiments
设计实验 以新的视角探索宇宙
in an effort to gain new insights into the way the world works.
卡文迪什其实不知道这些化学反应中到底发生了什么
Now, Cavendish didn't really have any idea what happened in these chemical reactions,
他全部的理论基础在现在看来都是错的
indeed his whole theoretical framework was nonsense to modernise,
它建立在炼金术的基础上
it was based on alchemy.
他当时认为物质会燃烧是因为它们含有一种叫燃素的成分
He thought things burned because they contained a substance called "phlogiston".
LOUD BANG
尽管这错得离谱
But even though that is complete nonsense,
但他是个优秀的实验科学家
because he was a great experimental scientist,
测量也十分准确 所以他成功测出
his measurements were correct, so he managed to measure that water
水是由两份氢和一份氧组成的 H2O
is made of two parts of hydrogen to one part of oxygen, H2O,
即使他根本就不相信水是由任何成组成的
even though he didn't believe that water was made of anything at all!
这种能力可以证明你关于宇宙运行
So, that ability to get your theoretical picture,
的理论认识和想法彻底错误
your ideas about the way that nature works completely wrong,
并且确保你的测量可靠准确
and yet make honest and precise measurements
足以接受时间的考验
that stand the test of time and are correct,
而这种能力恰恰是一位成功的实验科学家的标志
is the mark of a great experimental scientist.
毫无疑问 卡文迪什是英国史上最优秀的科学家之一
Cavendish has rightly gone down in history as one of this country's greatest scientists,
但他更多地被人们联想到
but perhaps he should be remembered more for his association
他和科学其他方面的联系
with another aspect of science,
因为他曾参与创立
because he was instrumental in establishing this place
位于伦敦阿尔伯马尔街21号的机构
at 21, Albemarle Street, London.
英国皇家研究所
The Royal Institution.
这个壁炉在英国科学史上占据重要位置
This fireplace occupies a central place in the history of British science.
它是一间位于索霍广场的房子的一部分
It was part of a house in Soho Square
而就在这间房子里 英国科学史上三位优秀的科学家
where three of the great characters in British scientific history
聚在一起 讨论着英国英国科学研究所的建设
gathered to discuss the foundation of this place, The Royal Institution.
这三人之一是伦福德伯爵
Those three men were Count Rumford of Bavaria,
他阅历丰富
who is a colourful character.
出生于美国 当过兵 搞慈善
He was born in America, he was a soldier, a philanthropist,
也是科学家和工程师 还是个花花公子
a scientist, an engineer. And many people say, a philanderer.
还有卡文迪什
Then there was Cavendish,
英国科学家和实验者中最古怪的人
that most eccentric of British scientists and experimenters.
最后还有约瑟夫・班克斯
And finally, there was Joseph Banks who is an iconic figure
18、19世纪科学的代表人人物
in 18th and 19th-century science.
他的科学生涯开始于1768年 他当时是一位植物学家
He began his scientific career as a botanist aboard the Endeavour
和库克船长一起乘坐奋进号前往大溪地岛
with Captain Cook in 1768 on the journey to Tahiti
观测金星移动
to measure the transit of Venus.
而他也不是众人眼中的科学家样子
And he was not a stereotypical scientist,
我见过人们这样描述他 头上的卷发犹如浓密的荆棘丛
I've seen him described as a man with a thick bramble of curly hair,
浑身散发着神秘和浪漫
he had a brooding, romantic intensity.
他说话方式更像呼啸山庄里的希斯克利夫
He sounds more like Heathcliff than a man of science.
尽管班克斯担任长达40年的科学研究所主席
But Banks, although he was president of The Royal Society for 40 years,
他仍热衷于使科学走向大众
was passionate about democratising science.
他认为英国科学有些与世隔绝
He felt that British science was to insular -
专属于富人和名人的 与达官贵人关系紧密
a preserve of the rich, famous, and politically well-connected.
因此这三人想以这个阶梯教室为中心
And so the three of them came up with the idea for this place,
建立这个研究所
centred around this lecture theatre.
他们希望公众可以在这了解得重大的科学发现
Where the vision was that the public could hear of the great discoveries of science.
英国皇家研究所成为了孕育
The Royal Institution became a platform for a new breed -
科学新人的摇篮
a science personality.
从与科学共舞的汉弗莱・戴维
From Humphry Davy, the showman who famously danced with joy at his scientific discoveries,
到开始“圣诞节讲座”传统
to Michael Faraday, who began the tradition
的迈克尔・法拉第
of giving the, now famous, Christmas lectures.
如今 科学家仍使用这间讲堂与公众互动
And the theatre is still used by scientists to engage with the public to this day.
如果现在我移除过滤器
If now I remove the filter...
LOUD BANG
将发生奇妙的事情
..something happens.
DULL BOOM
APPLAUSE
就在这样
Oh, yes!
APPLAUSE
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
请拿一些肥皂泡里的氢气
So, I'd like you to grab some of that hydrogen in the soap bubbles.
Um...
沃 噢 你还好吧
Whoa! Ow! You all right?
LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE
班克斯和他的团队是正确的 人们的确想
Banks and his colleagues were right, people really do want to hear
了解科学和工程上的发现
about the findings of science and engineering,
想了解宇宙探索
about the exploration of the universe.
在皇家研究所举办的公益讲座十分受欢迎
So popular were the public lectures here at the Royal Institution,
而阿尔伯马尔街也挤满了前来聆听讲座的马车
so crowded was Albemarle Street with horses and carriages delivering people to hear those lectures,
阿尔伯马尔街因此成为了伦敦的第一条单行道
that Albemarle Street had to be made the first one-way street in London.
英国帮助了科学方法的传播
Britain helped to give the world what we now call the scientific method.
诞生了如牛顿 卡文迪什这样
It produced great scientists like Newton and Cavendish
运用实验探究世界的科学家
who used experimentation to make discoveries.
英国率先认识到
It was amongst the first countries to understand
对科学的追求是国家实力的重要组成部分
that the pursuit of science is a vital part of nationhood,
而公众参与则保障了科学持续发展
and that public engagement ensures science's bloodline.
另一件发生在英国的事很可能
But there's another British phenomenon that has had perhaps
已深深影响了科学进步
the greatest impact on the progress of science,
那就是著述分享的简单行为
and that is the simple act of writing down and sharing ideas.
分享的源头可以追溯到
The roots of that sharing can be traced
科学史上某本里程碑似的著作
to one of the most iconic books in the history of science.
它极其珍贵 被存放在一间温度可控的地下室
It's considered so valuable that it's kept in a climate-controlled vault.
出版于1665年
Published in 1665, this is the first edition
第一期的英国皇家学会《自然科学会》
of the Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society.
它是第一本科学期刊
It is the first scientific journal.
我认为能够准确描述科学期刊是什么的人
And I think the best description of what scientific journals mean
非首任编辑奥尔登伯格莫属
should be left to the first editor, Oldenburg,
他写道 创立期刊的目的是
who wrote that the purpose of this
让科学家用自己的知识影响其他科学家
is to allow scientists to "impart their knowledge to one another
并为积累自然知识以及完善哲学和科学
"and contribute what they can to the grand design of improving natural knowledge
的伟大机制做出最大的贡献
"and perfecting all philosophical arts and sciences".
亨利・奥尔登伯格首次为科学家
Henry Oldenburg had created a platform, where for the first time,
提供交流彼此科学发现的平台
scientists could widely share their findings with others.
这就是出版和展示科学知识
So this is the publication, the presentation, of scientific knowledge
如果你走进这里 翻翻数年来出版的自然科学会报
and if you step through here and follow the Philosophical Transactions on through the years,
你会发现所有著名科学家都在这发表过自己的研究
you will find all the great names of science publishing their research in here for all to see.
有牛顿 有达尔文 有法拉第
So, you'll find Newton, you'll find Darwin, you will find Faraday,
这里就是存放所有人类拥有的知识的地方
this is where the sum total of human knowledge is stored and archived and rests.
科学史就在这呈献给大家
So, the history of science is laid out for everyone to see, here.
是不是很奇妙
Isn't that wonderful?
印刷第一期会报的将近350年之后
Nearly 350 years after that first issue was printed,
皇家学会依然在出版自然科学会报
the Royal Society still publishes its Philosophical Transactions,
而且每一期都会存放在这间图书馆里
and every issue of that journal is kept here in their library.
随便拿出一本
It's fascinating to just grab them at random.
这本出版于1897年 这上面写着
Here's one from 1897, and it's on,
我甚至看不懂这些字
I don't even know the words,
小脑传入和传出神经
"afferent and efferent tracks of the cerebellum",
和神经的再生
and the regeneration of nerves.
这本出版于1895年 有机草酰胺
And then you can go, here's one, 1895, "organic oxymides,
（完全不懂）
"or the organisation of the fossil plants of the coal measures".
显而易见 找到关于自然有趣的新发现
Now, obviously there's no point in finding interesting things out
而不告诉别人是没有意义的
about the natural world and keeping them to yourself,
而真正的意义就在于向公众展示这些发现
not telling anyone, but there's much more to publishing than that.
这期自然科学会报
This is an edition of the Philosophical Transactions
出版于1861年
of the Royal Society from 1861,
其中一篇约翰・丁达尔的文章
and one of the papers here by John Tyndall
就展示了
is one of the first pieces of research
如今被称为“温室效应”的早期研究
on what we now call the "greenhouse effect",
而温室效应则是气体会吸收热量
the way that different gases absorb heat.
好几个表格的实验结果
There is table after table of results,
他也准确讲述了他如何获得这些数据
but he also describes precisely how he got those results,
而且这张图也描绘了他的实验器材
and there's a beautiful diagram of his apparatus,
其他人如果怀疑数据结果的真实性
and this is there so that anyone else reading this paper, if they're sceptical about the results
或者仅仅是想验证一下 他们都可以自己搭建仪器
or even if they just want to check them, can rebuild the apparatus
重新做一次实验 看看丁达尔到底犯没犯错误
and redo the experiments and check that Tyndall didn't make any mistakes.
所有这些数据不是见仁见智的 它们就在这
So these results are not a matter of opinion, they're here,
已经被其他科学家检验过了 证实过了
they can be checked by other scientists, they can be verified.
这就是科学知识如何积累进步的
So, this is how scientific knowledge progresses.
出版就是解释科学为什么可以成为我们看待宇宙的最好方法的答案
Publishing is the reason why science gets to our best view of the way that nature works.
只从1665年第一期自然科学会报出版
Since the Philosophical Transactions emerged in 1665,
目前也出现方方面面的科学期刊
thousands of journals have been published on every aspect of science.
科学期刊因为备受信任正以此种方式蓬勃发展
Scientific journals have flourished in this way because they can be trusted.
期刊上出版的内容都尽可能接近事实陈诉
What's printed in them is as close to a statement of fact as you can hope for.
我可以完全相信科学
And we can trust in that science
原因就是诞生于英国的一种独特自我调节机制
thanks to a unique British-born system of self regulation
它扮演着十分重要的角色 那就是同行评审
that lies at its heart - peer review.
坎贝尔博士是现任《自然》杂志主编
Dr Philip Campbell is the editor in chief of the journal, Nature.
同行评审保障了
And peer review is central to its reputation
其作为世上之一最优秀的期刊的名誉
as one of the greatest journals in the world.
你能简单介绍一下同行评审吗
Could you run through the peer review process,
具体的流程的是什么
and describe exactly how that works?
同行评审是他的同事或同行
So, peer review is an attempt by colleagues, as it were, of the authors,
验证作者实验结果是否正确的尝试
their peers, to see whether what these authors have produced looks valid.
同行会认真阅读论文 抽丝剥茧
He or she will look at that and really rip it to shreds,
挖掘数据 然后反馈给我们
digging into the data and then coming back to us and saying,
我已经认真阅读了这篇论文 我认为这篇论文没有问题
"I've really looked at this stuff and it's stood up to what I thought."
或者他们说这篇论文有问题
Or they'll say it doesn't.
那么你如何客观地评价
So, how would you assess the effects of this,
同行评审的作用 它达到我们要求的目的了吗
of the peer review process, just objectively? Does it do what we all want it to do?
纯粹对科学知识的评价如何保证客观
Which is be absolutely objective in a pure assessment of where our scientific knowledge is.
也存在一些小缺陷 我这么认为
It's full of little holes, that's how I see it.
没有任何一种方法可以排除掉所有坏文章
There are all sorts of ways in which bad papers can slip through.
他还不完美 我相信它存在某种程度上的偏见
It's not perfect and I'm sure that there are degrees of bias.
但我更担心
But I would feel a lot more worried
大量撤回我们发表的论文
if we were retracting a lot of our papers.
其实我们也撤回了少量论文
Actually, we retract very few of our papers.
我相信原因是我们发表的论文基本上是经得起考验的
I believe that's because what we publish is, by and large, robust.
我认为没有人可以比科学家更具备批判性
I really cannot think of a more critically minded group of people than scientists.
同行评审不是科学出版提供的唯一一种方式
Peer review is not the only service provided by scientific publishing.
因为期刊是科学界主要的一种发声形式
Because the journals are one of the key voices of the scientific community,
为持续的辩论提供平台
providing a forum for continued debate.
这种科学界持续的评审帮助去伪存真
This continuous interrogation by the scientific community helps sort the good science from the bad.
这大体上提供了科学家
Gradually, this gives way to a consensus
针对最近发现及其意义达成共识的方法
with scientists agreeing on the latest findings and their meaning.
论文并不是终结
No paper is the end of the story.
即使一篇论文已经登上了自然
So, even though it's got the Nature name on it,
在我看来 只有人们确实验证了实验结果
from my point of view, I know that it's only when it's been out there
我们才能确信这篇文章是没有问题的
and people have really tested it and try to build on it, that we really know whether it's true.
全球变暖就是一个很好的例证
Global warming is a good example.
科学界的大部分达成共识二氧化碳
There's an overwhelming scientific consensus that carbon dioxide
和其他排入大气的气体正在改变气候
and other emissions into the atmosphere is changing the climate,
使全球变暖 人们是如何达成这个共识的
warming the world. So, how did that consensus develop?
气候系统非常复杂
The climate system is enormously complex
我认为没有任何一篇文章
and I don't think there is any single paper that can ever show
能描述清楚大气因为二氧化碳或其他温室气体
one way or another that climate warming because of carbon dioxide
的这种或那种变暖过程
or other greenhouse gases is occurring.
因此 花费了大量时间 积累了很多证据
So, it's only over a lot of time and a lot of cumulative evidence,
仔仔细细地检查 你才能最终确定
and a lot of critical scrutiny that you end up convinced
某事正在发生
that something is really happening.
我想说气候变化
I would so love to show that climate change isn't happening
并不会威胁我孙子孙女的未来
in a way that I do actually believe threatens my grandchildren's future.
但不幸的是
But, it's so unfortunate
我们似乎没有得到任何可以证明它是伪命题的文章
that we don't seem to be getting papers that show that it's wrong.
同行评审尝试向科学发现过程中
Peer review is an attempt to introduce
引入额外的严密审查
an additional level of rigour to the process of discovery,
让我们可以区分已验证的假设和推测
allowing us to distinguish between tested hypotheses and speculation.
书和期刊的不同之处在于
The difference between a book and a scientific journal
书里只是作者自己的观点
is that, in a book, you're reading an author's opinion.
世上可能没有赞成书中的内容 而且你也可能不知道
Nobody else in the world may agree with the contents of this book and you wouldn't know.
书只表达了个人观点
It's a statement of opinion.
虽然期刊经过了层层审核
Whereas a scientific journal has been through some level of checking,
此领域的专家仍会认真阅读 发现被人忽视的错误
experts in the field have looked at it and found that it's not obviously wrong.
所以说同行评审在某种意义上
So a scientific peer review journal is in a sense a snapshot
是任意时间我们对客观世界或某一特定事物的最佳理解的写照
of our best view of the world, of a particular subject, at any given time.
从牛顿的理性探讨到出版和同行评审
From Newton's rational approach, to publishing and peer review,
可以说英国对科学产生的影响是全世界最大的
Britain has arguably had a greater influence on how science is done than any other nation.
也许这种影响在法国更明显
But perhaps that legacy can be seen most clearly in France.
或是说 在法国
Or rather, UNDER France,
和瑞士地下
and Switzerland.
这些建筑看似毫不起眼
This rather unimpressive set of buildings
就像一所三等的省级技术院校
might look like a third-rate provincial technical college,
但里面住的可是正参加有史以来
but housed in them are scientists engaged in what is, without doubt,
最伟大实验之一的科学家
one of the most important experiments ever undertaken.
在底下大约100米 就是大型强子对撞机
Below the ground here, around 100 metres below the ground, is the Large Hadron Collider.
周长27千米
It's 27 kilometres in circumference.
它能将质子加速到光速的99.9999%
Its job is to accelerate protons to 99.9999% the speed of light,
一秒可以绕周长27千米的隧道11,000圈
at which speed they circumnavigate these 27 kilometres 11,000 times a second.
质子相互碰撞 模拟宇宙大爆炸最初的
The protons are collided together, and with each one of those collisions,
十亿分之一秒之内
the conditions that were present
这些碰撞发生了
less than a billionth of a second after the universe began, are recreated.
人类可能
The sheer audacity of it,
回到137年前探索宇宙如何形成
that human beings might be able to reach back 13.7 billion years
这种行为十分大胆 扣人心弦
to discover how the universe evolved, is breathtaking.
这里进行的实验定会载入史册
And yet, that's what's being done here on an epic scale.
大型强子对撞机是人类建造的最为复杂的实验设备
The Large Hadron Collider is the most complicated scientific experiment ever built.
但它仍和其他设备一样都是实验的一部分
But it's still just an experiment like any other.
它的核心还是可再现性
At its heart, there is repeatable process...
牛顿的棱镜核心也是可再现性
..as with Newton's prism.
正如卡文迪什一样
There are teams of people dedicated to making detailed measurements,
大量的团队都致力于做出精细测量
as Cavendish did with his flammable air.
LOUD BANG
塔特运用的严谨逻辑思考
And the same rigorously logical thought processes
也被应用在这里
used by Bill Tutte are, of course, applied here too.
这些原则原则虽然简单 但有着极大力量
These are simple principles, yet they hold great power.
世上半数的粒子物理学家 大约10,000人
Half of the world's particle physicists, 10,000 of them,
都因潜在科学发现的吸引 聚集在这
are gathered here because of the tantalising prospects of what they might discover.
欧洲核子研究组织就是未来 因为这里正经历着天翻地覆的变化
CERN is now the place to be because everything is happening here.
新物理 新材料 超对称 暗物质
New physics, new stuff, supersymmetry, dark matter.
我们正在解决的问题很重要 是世界万物的基础
So we're solving problems which are fundamental to all, all people, everywhere.
你不会在意他们来自哪里 我们都在为同一个目标努力
You don't really care where anyone comes from, we all want the same thing.
能成为其中一部分
And being part of this
简直太奇妙了
is just...brilliant.
我在干什么 我得想一想
What do I do? I'm going to have to think about that for a second...
HE CHUCKLES
尽管其中一两位科学家
But while one or two of them
记不住他们自己应该干什么
can't remember what they're supposed to be doing individually,
但作为一个集体 这的科学家们
as a group, the scientists here
已做出物理上的重大发现之一
have made one of the most important discoveries in physics.
日内瓦欧洲核子研究组织的研究人员
Researchers at the Centre for Nuclear Research near Geneva...
就在几分钟前宣布他们已经观测到
..have just announced in the last few minutes that Higgs boson,
被称为上帝粒子的希格斯玻色子
the so-called God particle, has been glimpsed.
2012年7月 已证实检测到一种新的粒子 希格斯玻色子
In July 2012 it was confirmed that a new particle, the Higgs boson, had been detected.
亚原子拼图中的这种难捉摸的一小片
This elusive piece of the subatomic jigsaw
是宇宙万物一切质量的来源
is responsible for the masses of the building blocks of the universe.
这种粒子以英国物理学家彼得・希格斯命名
The particle is named after British physicist Peter Higgs,
希格斯早在50年前就在研究这种理论
who worked on the theory some 50 years earlier.
此项理论是CERN的构想的辩护
The discovery is a vindication of the ideas behind CERN,
我们之所以相信这项发现
but the reason that we can be confident in the discovery
是因为在实验设计中投入的心血
is the painstaking effort that has gone into the design of the experiments.
即使资助两个研究团队 而他们却在研究同一件事情
Even to the point of funding two separate teams of researchers, analysing exactly the same things.
因为交叉核对十分重要 不允许团队讨论自己研究
A cross-check so vital that the teams are not allowed to discuss their work,
即使团队间讨论也不被允许
even with each other.
我所在的研究所就是那边几百米的
My institute in Manchester is part of an experiment
超环面仪器实验中的一部分
about a few hundred metres in that direction called Atlas,
它集结了来自38个国家超过160个学术机构
it's a collaboration of over 160 institutes from 38 countries,
我们一起设计 建造 运行这个实验
and together, we designed, we built and we operate that experiment.
如果你朝这个方向走上几英里
Now, if you go several miles in that direction,
大型强子对撞机的另一边还有另一个合作研究所
over to the other side of the LHC there's another collaboration.
也就是CMS 由另一批物理学家负责
It's called CMS and it's run by different physicists.
它的设计 建立 运行 完全独立于Atlas
It was designed, built, and it is operated completely independently from Atlas.
它们都在研究同一种物质
But they're both designed essentially to do the same thing,
也就是研究类似希格斯玻色子的物理新现象
which is to search for new physics like the Higgs boson.
由于两个团队找到了完全一样的物质
And because these two groups found exactly the same thing,
因此每个人都确信该粒子确实已经被发现了
everyone could be confident that the Higgs really had been discovered.
就是这种科学方法让CERN
It's this, the scientific method, that gives CERN
和所有的科学研究相信其拥有的力量和正确性
and all of scientific investigation its power and validity.
CERN就是现代科学的最好例证
CERN is the best example of what modern, international science has become
你会发现所有的基本科学准则
and you see all the basic principles of science
都已付诸实践 从精确观察到同行评审
put into action here, from precision observation to peer review.
英国在超过四个世纪中奉献给科学的东西
So, I suppose, CERN perfectly embodies all the things that Britain
现在都被CERN传承了下来
over four centuries has given to science.
科学就是这个国家拥有的其中一个成功故事
Science is one of this country's success stories,
许多知名人物都是英国人
many of its important characters are British,
英国也成为重大科学发现的摇篮
and Britain has always been a place where crucial discoveries are made.
牛顿的万有引力定律 原子结构
Newton's theory of gravity, the structure of the atom,
DNA分子模型
the form of the DNA molecule,
北大西洋上的这些小岛留下的所有遗产
all courtesy of a few small islands in the North Atlantic.
但是重大的科学发现都不是巧合
But these great discoveries haven't happened by accident.
皇家学会和科学研究所这样组织的存在
The existence of organisations like the Royal Society
证明了英国重视科学头脑
and the Royal Institution demonstrates that here is a place where enquiring minds are valued,
也相信看似未知的事物也值得研究
and the apparently unknowable is thought worthy of investigation.
这是一个歌颂好奇心的国家
This is also a nation that celebrates curiosity,
一旦和正确的探索自然的方法结合
and when combined with a powerful method to investigate nature,
英国科学定会
this has always ensured that British science
屹立世界之巅
is disproportionately represented amongst the world's best.
英国 仅有世界1%的人口和3%的投资
Britain, with only 1% of the world's population and 3% of the investment,
发表了将近15%的最具影响力的科学论文
produces almost 15% of the most influential scientific papers.
考虑到我们的文明就建立在科学的基础上
And given that our civilisation is built on science,
科学使我们了解自然的唯一方法
that science is the only way we have of understanding how nature works,
英国今天在世界科学中
then it seems to me that Britain's place today
占据的领先地位
as the best place in the world to do science
似乎值得庆祝 值得投入
is something that's worth cherishing, investing in,
值得保护
and protecting for the future.
下一集 我们将走进英国重大科学发现的发生地
Next time, I'll be looking at where some of Britain's greatest discoveries came from.
当我们知道自己在寻找什么时 科学给我们带来的好处是不是更多
And asking whether we benefit more from science when we know what we looking for.
或者这些想法是不是从天而降
Or whether the best ideas come out of the blue.